[Music]
chocolate
it creates a feeling of happiness
a temporary cause and effect
by the organic compounds and the
chocolate itself
if you're new to the channel we make ice
cream
we make our own flavors we make ben
jerry's haagen-dazs jenny's salt and
straw ample hills you name it we go
through the lot
we break down their flavors
and see how or try and see how they've
done it and then hopefully help you
create them at home
every saturday we release a video that
is somehow about ice cream so if that's
something that will float your boat
don't forget to hit that subscribe
button
and comment below on what your favorite
ice cream flavor is
so with all that in mind
welcome to episode one of our new
chocolate ice cream series
in this series we're gonna break down
the reasons why chocolate is such a
difficult ice cream to make well
as this is episode one we're gonna start
with some basics and a bit of science
and hopefully get you on the track to
making the perfect chocolate ice cream
at home
okay
just reminds me of breaking bad
methylamine
anyway
phenylethylamine
caffeine and magnesium all contribute to
the effect chocolate has on your brain
and the fener
phenylethylamine blimey
that is said to dilate the blood vessels
in your brain which actually induce
headaches and migraines in some people
that effect is compounded by chocolate
being warm which is why if you suffer
from headache headaches and migraines
you're much better off eating chocolate
that's been kept in the fridge
there was one canadian study examining
the link between chocolate and happiness
there was no conclusive results to this
study unfortunately because the control
group that didn't have chocolate
raided the fridge and ate all the
chocolate that was there in storage what
does this tell us it tells us that if
you really want chocolate you're pretty
prepared to do whatever it takes to get
it
there are awful lot of different
chocolate brands and types out there way
too many for us to go through here
but
we're going to look at some now and just
talk about the differences quickly
lots of chocolate
a very small bar of dairy milk there
i bought that just for christmas and
i've
[Music]
eaten most of it
anyway these are all different these are
all i mean
white is technically not chocolate but
it's always described as a chocolate 70
you've got your 55s your 35s
dairy milk is summer in the 20s late 20s
this complete cheap chocolate
100 chocolate designed for cooking i
mean you can use this in
in savory dishes as well these are all
very very different
they have different cocoa solid contents
different milk contents different sugar
contents all of this will have an effect
on your ice cream we're gonna go through
that in the next video so
click that subscribe button so you don't
miss out so now that the chocolate part
is out the way let's get on to the cocoa
powder part let's get some in so we can
talk about them
cocoa powder
[Music]
different types of cocoa powder with
different fat contents different
intensities of flavor
some that aren't even cocoa powder these
are just drinking chocolates which are
mostly sugar so if you use these to
flavor your chocolate ice cream you're
really going to struggle to balance that
recipe this one is an intense black
cocoa powder with about a 12 to 13 fat
content tastes disgusting
unless you boil it within an inch of its
life
all of these things again will have an
impact on your chocolate ice cream
we will go through these again like the
chocolate in the next video of this
chocolate ice cream series
with that in mind let's get into some
science shall we
so
what exactly is ice cream
it's a combination of water fat
protein sugars air
and emulsifiers sometimes stabilizers
sometimes
that's what it is it doesn't sound very
appetizing
but let's look into those individual
elements and actually see what they mean
so the water the fats proteins
some sugars anyway
will all come from dairy unless you're
making vegan of course
now you will need to increase the sugars
and you'll need to increase solids but
again we'll go through that in in the
next video
[Music]
but if you combine those ingredients add
a little bit more sugar maybe the odd
egg yolk here and there for
emulsification purposes
churn it in your ice cream machine
you've got ice cream it really is that
simple
and once you've created your very basic
or sweet cream base as often described
if you want to make a chocolate ice
cream you need to add either physical
chocolate melted into the base whilst
you're heating up or cocoa powder
that is where the fun begins
so let's assume you have your favorite
vanilla ice cream recipe and you've used
it a hundred times before and it's
perfect you love it
if you wanted to create a chocolate ice
cream you decided to add cocoa powder or
chocolate that's melted to that to
create a chocolate ice cream
what is likely going to happen is your
balanced vanilla recipe is then going to
get really high in solids or sugar
and will either freeze too hard or won't
freeze at all
that is the fun that chocolate fun
that chocolate ice cream can do for you
it can take a very simple
tried and tested recipe and turn it
completely on its head
the internet
it's full of recipes mostly bad if you
google chocolate ice cream recipes you
are going to come across a wash of
really bad ice cream recipes i mean some
of them even say to leave your ice cream
out of the freezer for 20 minutes before
you can scoop it i mean really is that a
joke
after 20 minutes i've eaten my ice cream
and probably gone on to some chocolate
or something else
20 minutes
that's not right when you want ice cream
you want to go to the freezer take out
the tub get scooping and eat straight
away every single ice cream recipe you
create you should really balance it and
that just means getting all the
ingredients in the right amount so they
all work together to create the perfect
finish for you
how you balance an ice cream recipe
we'll go into that now
so i use two different ice cream
calculators one is actually quite
confusing to people if you're new to ice
cream or you're not very tech savvy but
it is by far the best ice cream
calculator out there i'll put a link
below to that i also use a really simple
one from dreamscoop's website
it doesn't go into anywhere near as much
detail but it's really handy if you just
want to create an ice cream and know
that it's going to be balanced
this is how
we use it what you need to do is adjust
the milk fat percentage and cream fat
percentage of the products that you're
using at home then add in your cocoa
powder fat percentage now below that you
can start adding the approximate amounts
of each ingredient you want to try and
use that includes your milk cream sugars
and cocoa powder and down below you can
see some basic numbers and that's the
fat percentage milk solids non-fat sugar
other solids and total solids now just
play with the amounts until you reach
the numbers that you want dream scoops
give you some examples underneath and
the other ice cream calculator really go
into detail as to what each one does for
you
so now that we've established how you
control your ice cream recipe
let's look back at one of our older
flavors that we did jenny's darkest
chocolate or nyx darkest chocolate
whatever way you want to shake it
the recipe for nyx darkest chocolate and
jenny's darkest chocolate are designed
to break the rules for ice cream they're
very high in solids which would make it
freeze rock solid if it weren't for
additional sugars in there as well
the sugars depress the freezing point
and make it more scoopable straight from
the freezer
now high solids can actually create a
fudgy texture to your chocolate ice
cream which i love and i know a lot a
lot of other people like it as well
that's a desirable effect that high
solids can have on your chocolate ice
cream you can recreate that by using
certain stabilizers as well later down
this series we'll talk about just
stabilizers and how they work with
chocolate ice cream
so now that a lot of you are most
probably confused as to why chocolate is
so difficult to make unless you think
it's easy of course then good stuff
in four weeks time we'll release the
second episode of our chocolate ice
cream series where we'll go through the
variables we'll go through the chocolate
the cocoa powders the dairy the sugars
and how they all collect together and
the different effects they'll have while
you're making it
so for now thanks very much for watching
don't forget to like and subscribe and
come and see us next week when we make
salt and straws cinnamon snickerdoodle
ice cream sounds good
[Music]